so
everybody welcome to this episode of the
wasabi wallet research experience
this is our weekly research call where
we talk about all the crazy things
happening in the bitcoin rapido
and we can use them to improve the
bitcoin privacy for many users
uh and today we got the the usual
reckless crew on board but also
two special guests from short bits we
have nadav cohen
and ben the carmen how are you both
doing good thanks for having us yeah
you have uh really cool so maybe we can
just get going with
a quick introduction of what is the the
very general overview of discrete law
contracts uh that you're working on the
circuits
and like the highest level explanation
is just you have a
bitcoin contract or a bitcoin
transaction
that's contingent on an oracle or
set of oracles attesting to an outcome
so you do something basic like betting
on the super bowl
or something more complex doing like you
know an options contract on the bitcoin
price
so um with the actually like what you're
betting on and what the oracle is
signing is kind of limitless
and it's just like what you can build on
top of that
yeah i have a question first question
and what
are in your opinion the most um
obvious um usage of this technology
for example betting is one that you just
mentioned
what other um
things can be done with this technology
i mean something that's coming out soon
is uh if you saw atomic finances
releasing their
options to like trading with uh dlcs
so that'll be a way where like people
can like buy and sell
covered calls um on like directly on
bitcoin without needing to use an
exchange which i think will be pretty
cool
you also use the this for things like
insurance
or things like uh
just like basically any existing
financial contract that you have or like
something like derivatives or
you can also use it to like hold other
assets for like something we did
so we've like basically created a
synthetic dollar by
just like um having your payout be
like you know you start with like fifty
dollars with the bitcoin and you end
with fifty dollars worth of bitcoin and
um so you do that but
without dollars you could do that with
apple stock you could do that with like
literally anything so
and kind of the the possibilities are
kind of limitless it's just um
figuring out how to how to do all these
things i don't know did not
adapt you have anything to add
um yeah i mean i think you hit all the
really obvious ones we already know
about betting trading hedging
and uh i guess synthetic assets
and in in this case the
the contract has two two parties right
i mean it's two two people involved uh
in most of the financial contracts there
are
also two people involved but given there
is a
high liquidity it's transparent for you
you don't need to
find someone to to to make a
this contract there is a system that can
find
the content the counterparty for you
right
that if you want to sell for example
what you what you
want sorry what you have
do you think these contracts
um can replace that kind of
or can be used to build this kind of
high liquidity
and very fast kind of trading of
futures or whatever
yeah so i think um to some extent
the answer is yes especially once we
have dlcs on lightning
and we can uh do things like uh
cooperative transfers as well
um and you know of course we need some
kind of matching mechanism and there are
lots of ways
to to go about uh approaching that
problem
but i will say i i mean at the end of
the day
i think there will be lots and lots of
use cases for dlcs
but i expect there will still be some
amount
of more centralized solutions that
people
want to use in in cases where
they they're willing to take on um
or in the cases where the trade-offs
that that dlcs take
uh don't make sense for them and they
they want to use like a centralized
uh third party or something like that
yeah like we'll never rival the like
nasdaq execution time but
um you know they'll never rival our you
know self-sovereignty version of it so
you know it's really like what the user
wants
okay max just in case jump
whenever you want i i can make questions
all this
all the day right but now i have another
question
because this was implemented this is
something that
exists today i know it's available right
but it is not using
i think it's not signatures
right um
just that's first if that is correct
how can this contract
change when that route is merged and
available for the bitcoin network
and uh you can probably answer this
better than me you're right at the
moment all right
um yeah yeah so right now uh we're not
using schwaron chain
um it's uh we're using ecdsa adapter
signatures
and uh once we have taproot then
uh we can use schnorr on chain and use
snore adapter signatures which will
be much much nicer they're like
nearly three times smaller much faster
to compute much faster to verify
and since these are like the things that
you're
building to sign all the off-chain
transactions like you're dealing with
like
tens of thousands sometimes more of
these signatures
per dlc uh at least if you're doing like
financial contract stuff
or numeric contract stuff i should say
um
and so one question you said that
the ecds adapter signatures are three
times larger
uh but aren't like is this the unchained
data that's three times larger compared
to
tap no no so adapter signatures aren't
valid on
chain uh adapter signatures are kind of
an entirely off-chain construct
that's uh very closely related to the
on-chain signature scheme
um yeah so actually uh
adapter signatures for ecdsa you have
your like
65 byte like actual signature
i mean it's not ddr encoded but whatever
um and then you have like a 97 byte zero
knowledge
proof of discrete log equality or poodle
um and uh yeah so
so there's there's kind of extra steps
because we're going through ecdsa
whereas in schnorr you just have the
nice little 64 byte
adapter signature um and then also all
of the computations on those are much
faster
or at least significantly faster so
that's that's kind of the first
nice thing and then the the other nice
thing though i'm not sure
whether or not we will or you know when
we'll get around to utilizing this but
you can use adapter signatures and snore
with key aggregation which is
just crazy significantly harder
in ecdsta so right now with ecdsa
adapter signatures
we are using single signer ecdsa adapter
signatures so that
we we need like a two of two on chain
but with taproot that can also just
become like a single pub key
on chain so long term for dlcs in
in a tap root uh
a dlc on chain looks like
some money moving into one pub key and
then moving
out to two other pub keys and that's all
there is to it on chain there's nothing
else that shows up on chain
okay and just to confirm right now you
have the multi-six script on chain
yeah right now it looks like some fun's
moving into a two of two and then
leaving to two outputs so it kind of
looks like a lightning open close
i mean you could use two-party ecdsa to
compress that to a single pup p2
why did you not do that for this mvp
because i want to sleep at night
yeah i mean the the dirty secret
is that you know basically anything you
can do with schnorr you can do with
ecdsa
it's just very easy
to get wrong like at every stage
and it's just a much larger attack
surface
and implementation complexity and
getting people to look at that code is
very hard and all the other kind of
challenges
that go with it so yeah yeah and taproot
makes it obsolete so
that's right
okay one more i i think i know the
answer but
these contracts are not easy to identify
or
i i think it's not probably possible to
identify
in unchained right i mean if there is a
transaction that basically i
was betting something to max and
max won the bet and
the transaction is it's
not i cannot
say of observing the transaction on
chain
i cannot say hey this is a payment to
max
right no not at all like
the oracle can't tell you're using them
um only
the only people i could tell is like you
and your counterparty
it's literally just like a 202 multi-sig
so people
probably think it's a lightning like
channel at first
because that's way more common than dlcs
at the moment
but yeah it's like very very private in
that way
exactly but with top truth you will not
even be able to say this is a two
parties a multi-signature it's just a
normal transaction
isn't it or am i wrong no that's correct
yeah
with like in the like you know years
from now when we have like full taproot
support yeah it'll look like just
you know like two like two uh two inputs
fund this
uh this pub key and then pub key
sends out to you know two other outputs
and
you know very it could be like a user
wallet it could be
someone consolidating etx says it could
be whatever it's just it looks very
it could be another change yeah it could
be a payment would change it could be
anything so
it'll be very hard to tell what's going
on can it actually
be a pain like do you think that the
software will be in a way that the
withdrawal transaction can be to an
arbitrary address
even to a third party who was not
involved in the contract in the first
place
i don't see why not like you just
specify an address for your payout so
you could set it to like instead of
bringing it to your own wallet
set it to you know deposit to like
your friend or deposit to an exchange or
whatever you want
yeah and in the future uh or so first of
all just to have it
out outcuts go to you know more than two
parties
is is quite simple uh i mean it's not
implemented or specified right now but
totally possible if there was a use case
that wouldn't be a hard thing to add um
and then on top of that
uh in the future we'll probably have
more multi-party dlc stuff
available anyway so yeah i think that
uh you you can intermingle kind of
payments with these things as well
well it's very interesting because you
know that
we like things that
when you cannot say what is going on on
chain
we like it right so i was imagining that
probably if we have a
huge amount of these transactions that
you cannot
say what is happening
who is paying whom uh it could be used
for
i mean it has privacy applications
probably
have you something in mind
have you discussed this um properties
before i'm sure you you did can you
share
share with us your thoughts about
this property for privacy
and i think it's huge for privacy just
like being able to do financial
contracts where
no one but your counterparty knows
what's going on like today
you know you have to like go through a
financial institution to be able to do
really anything and you get kyc didn't
all that versus this like
it's completely permissionless and open
all you need is like some stats to open
up the
contract so i think that'll i think like
one of the huge things is like
today in the world we have like the us
financial institution that's like
has like all the network effects and
money and like if you can't get access
to that you kind of get boned in the
traditional finance world but with this
like you know you could be some
like guy in nigeria with just an
internet connection and some bitcoin and
like
have like you know all those financial
products now
i i have a more concrete question how
much
i have to trust on the oracle
um i mean it depends so you can
you don't have to use a single oracle
you can use multiple so like what we
released
last week was we did like a two of three
setup where
if two of three oracles agreed on a
average bitcoin price
then our contract could execute but so
you don't need to trust like a single
oracle completely
but at the end of the day like your
oracle or a set of oracles
completely was gonna dictate your
outcome so like if they're all hacked or
regulated or
go offline like your contract is screwed
and there are ways to like
um you could like since it is just a 202
multistick you can collaborate with your
counterparty
to close it in a different way or we do
have like a
predefined refund so if the oracle never
signs anything you get your money back
but um you know the oracle can
like you know if you're using a single
oracle and they sign the wrong outcome
like
that's just going to be what it is and
you're kind of screwed there
yeah i will note though so it is true
that your your contracts that you have
open
that the oracles if they lie or are
corrupted or
something like this um if if that
happens
the the oracles or sorry the oracle
contracts that were based on that
specific event
get wrecked but um
the kind of oracle model for dlcs has
kind of users as entirely private
entities and
oracles as entirely public and oblivious
entities
so it has first of all the nice property
that
oracle's don't know anything about their
users um
off the bat or at least it's it's very
tricky for them to
learn anything about their users um
and how they're being used and if
they're being used in these kinds of
things
um which which is nice you know i always
tell people that when you're dealing
with oracles and
trust models in general like privacy is
a part of security
um it's just part of the security model
but then on top of that
um because oracles are public entities
uh in in dlcs there is no real way for
them to lie
privately if you get um
you know if oracle that you're using
lies even if they like say lie privately
to your counterparty
you can recover that live from on chain
information
using uh the off chain information that
you have
from the transaction that your
counterparty uses
so at the end of the day you can still
construct publicly verifiable fraud
proofs that um the oracle attested to
something that was false
or or equivocated or something like this
um and so in the future i think that
there will be
lots of ways for oracle's to essentially
you know put their money where their
mouth is and stake funds that
can be taken away from them if they lie
because
at the end of the day and even if if
that's not the case you know just from
like a
more reputation perspective like it's
impossible for them to lie in private
essentially is a nice property of dlcs
yeah really cool i have one more
question on the more on chain layer
so the funding transactions into that
uh the display block script has
uh two inputs from or an input from each
user
right so at least one might provide at
least one in the same transaction
and then the nice thing is this also
breaks the common input on the ship our
state
and it's same as light is dual funded
lightning or pay joint
right so this is actually a nice benefit
for on-chain privacy in general yeah i
think this is really huge where you kind
of get like a
a mini coin join there and uh something
that
i wrote a while back but i think where
you could do like
i call it a chaomian dlc where you could
batch a whole bunch of dlcs together
and then like you have like a basically
a whole bunch of inputs going into like
a bunch of different dlcs all in one
giant transaction and
now you like really break the uh common
input heuristic there
yeah exactly right that's the logically
following next question
i'm curious maybe uh yuval or nada have
interesting points on the nuances of
coin joints with dlcs
yeah i mean i think uh
i think like it's um it's theoretically
possible to be able to like have a
like similar like wasabi's model where
you have like a coordinator
but instead of this coordinator just
giving and passing around
um details about the coin transaction
you guys would also pass around uh
stuff about your dlc and um the nice
thing too with this is the
coordinator could actually close the
contract for you
if they are connected to the oracle so
there's some like actual
ux improvements there too where you know
you don't need to be online and actually
close your own
dlc yeah the with the gist of it is just
like you know you set up
or like you say have like 50
participants all doing
a contract and then they um take this
take one side of the bet the other they
say like half take one
size bit half take the other and then
they all register inputs
and basically just create a giant dlc
and then all the payouts go out um at
the
at the end i don't know yeah but one
note here is that if
all of the users of this coin joints use
dlc
then it's kind of like a bad fingerprint
in terms that you know that for 100 sure
this is a dlc contract
right well if if there are other non-dlc
users in the same coin joint
right then because of tamproot this is
uh they look the same
and this would be huge because then you
don't know which user is part of the dlc
which has to pay join a uh malt
consolidation
right and that would improve uh like
analysis massively for everyone i think
yeah i think uh that that that's totally
doable and we've we've thought about
kind of this where you can
just mix pools where you have people who
are doing dlcs with people who are doing
coin joins with people who are opening
lightning channels or
in the more distant future channel
factories and
all these kinds of things at the end of
the day you can always
just like save a little bit on fees by
throwing everyone's inputs and outputs
on the same transaction
of course with dlcs in particular um
uh there are ways around this where you
can kind of have like a multi-stage
setup kind of closer to how uh
they've been working on putting multiple
lightning funding transactions
multiple lightning channel opens in the
same transaction you could do something
like that with dlcs
and coin joins and all just kind of in
one
transaction um but if you wanted to
actually mix
kind of normal coinjoin users with um
dlc users then there is kind of the
i suppose maybe not for everyone this is
a downside but the downside of like
there's a long time between um
going on chain and paying out
um because uh you have to wait for like
the
oracle event to happen or something like
this but you know if someone's mixing
coins they don't need to
be sending anywhere anytime soon then
maybe this isn't a big deal
it's actually a cool privacy benefit of
having time staggered remixes
and it could increase your unknown too
yeah i think that could be really big
too because like
i mean the only downside there is that
like at least
in today's coin joins you would have to
like
you know you have to use the same output
amount less like so if you're doing like
wasabi has to be like you know like the
0.1 bitcoin
but uh i mean what's the stuff you guys
are working on with
wabi-sabi you kind of try to fix this
yeah
he fixes this and uh yeah then you could
do an entire thing where
you know you could have any contract
really going in on there and
really privately with everyone else's
transaction that'd be awesome
yeah and uh another thing i just
realized
that i forgot to mention uh that is like
a benefit of doing things this kind of
way at least for dlc
users is if you have
you can essentially use netting
while you're doing this so if i have a
position
open with two different people who are
also participating here
and there's like some overlap happening
then
really all that needs to happen in the
more coin join looking
transaction is kind of the aggregation
so i can like
recover some collateral or things like
this
yeah especially with wabi-sabi that
allows for multiple outputs being
registered at different values
right um i like consolidation
of multiple refunds or payouts
can be done too maybe i mean
they're in the nuances of course like
how much information does the
coordinator learn
that's something that you want to figure
out i guess
um as far as i can tell i
[Music]
there shouldn't be any uh requirement
for the coordinator to be involved at
all
um there might be added value like if
the coordinator is also
helping to mediate this kind of uh net
settlement or
like making the actual outputs uh
allocations more efficient
that might be a good reason to uh
involve the coordinator but
um i'm a little bit rusty about dlcs but
if i understand correctly the the way
that you would do such a thing is
two users would just register their
funding amounts
uh to a wabi-sabi coin join uh they
would negotiate the off chain
contract um uh and then at the signing
phase
once the transaction id is uh already
locked in
assuming only segwit uh inputs are
allowed into the transaction um at that
point the
um like refund transactions and stuff
like that exactly like a lightning
channel can be
uh pre-signed uh before both uh parties
to the coinjoin
uh provide their coinjoin signatures so
at least in theory it it should you know
already be
possible uh you spoke about the
deposit into the dlc but what about the
payout and the withdrawal of the dlc
uh if i understand correctly uh that
um like the once the
the two of two like output is is already
locked in and funded
um the oracle will uh publish its uh
uh attestation i guess for lack of a
better term sorry about that
um and then uh one of the parties to the
transaction will be able to unilaterally
uh spend that at that point uh
especially if it's a taproot output of
course they could uh negotiate to uh
just do uh like a a a payout
a transaction that spends that um
much like uh coin swap uh settlements
work
um and equally uh they could you know
uh bilaterally agree to register this
output
uh as an input to a subsequent coin join
if uh complex scripts are are
implemented um like if if you're able to
do
um arbitrary input uh types and not just
uh segwit pay to witness pubkey hash
inputs to coinjoin transactions
uh then at that point um like it
there's no difference right like the
ownership proof is equivalent to
the collaborative uh spend path um
and uh yeah it's just a matter of the
the two parties um like agreeing
who actually uses the credentials to to
register outputs um but that's
um like there's no theft risk there
but to build on top of that because
nadav said that there is this ux
improvement that the coordinator can
automatically take the oracle signature
and to
initiate the withdrawal transaction but
i am not sure how this would work with
coin joints
in a non-custodial way because you you
cannot
pre-sign the conjuring transaction
because you don't know the contract
transaction
so how would that work they couldn't
close it
in a coin join transaction for you but
like if they had
your like um outcome signatures and then
they got the oracle signature they could
close it and like the
um like in the easy case where it's just
like a single transaction that just has
the output to the winner
but um if you wanted to do like the coin
join like uh
clothes you'd have to like do that
cooperatively with
your counterparty so i think another
thing to mention i i kind of mentioned
that there are two different ways of
doing this one of them
is closer to like the multiple lightning
channel openings which i think is what
we're currently discussing
where you have a a bunch of inputs and
then a bunch of two of two outputs
but on another way of doing this that i
think ben has proposed
um which has its own trade-offs is
having a bunch of inputs and then a
single n of n output
uh and then a single transaction
spending that n of n
output in the end which closes all of
the
dlcs and this would be kind of the
situation where
it would make a lot of sense to
have a coordinator be able to just
broadcast that
mass closing something you could also do
is um well maybe not but um you could
like
just have your counterparty's signature
be
um have the same cash flag for um
single so it's only committing to the
payout output and then you could put
that output in the coinjoin transaction
the only problem is though then you're
if you're using that say cast flag
you're kind of revealing which output is
yours
um so maybe that wouldn't be the best
but you're still kind of you know
at least just saving on fees that way by
you know
sharing all the metadata in the
transaction yeah and it is important to
note that
um for this nfn scheme to work you do
gain some information about like the
other people in the mix because
uh you know what their outputs would be
on
oracle outcomes but there are a couple
ways to
mitigate this i don't think this has
been well thought out or modeled yet
but you can for example have rather than
one output per per participant
you can have multiple outputs where
essentially if you picture
like say the oracle outcome uh on on
like a
each party has a payout curve you can
decompose that payout curve into like
some wave functions or something like
that
where each output looks like nonsensical
essentially
uh and you don't know which aggregation
of outputs corresponds to like which
entity or
things like this um or there are a
couple other ways of
kind of trying to do obfuscation um
where you can have like
canceling noise on multiple outputs
but um again this hasn't been thought
out
too well yet also i think another
possible way you could do it is um
and once you have the tap your thing we
just have like a single key behind
the the funding output you could um in
the cases where
a single party gets all the winnings you
could instead of have
signing a transaction um on upon getting
the oracle signature you could have them
get just get um the other user's private
key
and then you could use that to then um
so then they could
then they just own the input completely
unilaterally and they could use that to
register for a coin join and just like
spend it from there
however they see fit
and one of the other kind of constraints
that i see is the coordination
complexity
and how much that increases when like
two users need to collaboratively look
at the coin join
and only after they have come to an
agreement
sign the conjoint uh so like what do you
think
will this lead to more like failed
signing rounds just because the users
don't
communicate properly
so i think um with dlcs
you have
you're signing so many things um i i
don't
think that uh adding this this coin
joining
stuff really has a significant increase
in how many things you are signing
uh and validating and such it uh could
change like the size of the thing you
have to validate
when before you sign say or or the thing
you have to hash before you sign
rather um but at the end of the day
like even for example for like the nfn
scheme
where they're like for every possible
you know or for every relevant possible
oracle outcome
you have um a separate closing
transaction for all end parties
um if you were doing just a two-party
dlc
in the usual way you would still have to
sign that many things
or at least on the same order of
magnitude um
and and so you know i think at least in
kind of a coordinated model it's not a
big difference where where you have
uh some kind of like one party that is
communicating with many other parties
um if it's more of like a gossip
based mixing protocol then this might be
significantly harder
uh maybe a more concrete question so if
uh
not often i want to fund this dlc
contract
we register our inputs in the coin join
um that we want to use in the deposit uh
in the next round we register
our output address which is one
incorporative
or like one of our cooperative dlc
contracts
and two changes for each other company
and then finally this gets put together
by the coordinator and we go into
signing phase
and now both enough and i have the coin
join transaction
which we will use to do the pre-signed
refund transactions
and all the dlc stuff that needs to be
done and then after all these refunds
are signed
then we put our final signature on the
chlorine joint
um like both of us on our own individual
utxos
and register them in signature
registration
is that roughly correct
yeah that that sounded right to me
yeah i think you could because like um
like with that multi-oracle
dlc that mean adopted last week like it
took us like
five minutes to sign everything um we
still have some optimizations to do to
make that
faster and by some he means all it will
be much faster
but uh it's still like you know it's not
as fast as um
like because i think like in wasabi you
have like what 20 seconds or something
to sign
so i actually think it's a three-minute
timeout for the signature basically
so that'll be good okay so maybe but
yeah something you could do like if it
was like
you know if you were pushing on that
threshold because you do need this
both parts do need to sign and verify
each other's stuff
so um something you could do is just um
you just give each other the refund
transaction signatures
and then once the funding transaction is
confirmed or like you know after
it's been at least broadcast then you
can start doing your
outcome signatures so at least that way
um
you know you're guaranteed to get your
money back if something goes wrong
um i think that has a bunch of free
option problems probably
but um yeah yeah probably yeah
but but i do think um that if if
it's a three minute timeout in the
future this this isn't going to be a
problem
like we have lost i'm actually not sure
what it will be in the future
but i think right now it's three minutes
what are your thoughts on signing
period timeout um
so generally i would say um
[Music]
it's probably going to be variable like
uh we've been thinking about scenarios
like
pspt support or hardware wallet support
uh and if it's psbt support for like a
manual thing
you know maybe some rounds would even
have a signing phase that's on the order
of
hours for uh you know high value coin
joins or something like that
um i i think that's something that
uh even if the wasabi coordinator um
doesn't deviate from the current timeout
values
uh and there's demand i'm sure that some
coordinator would
come up and uh offer those round
parameters
cool yeah so i mean dlcs
require i i assume at least usually less
time
than uh using like a hardware wallet so
that's good to hear
for what it's worth like one idea we
were kind of spitballing
is um having the like
um making all the coordinator uh rounds
basically determinable by the users so
if there's no round available right now
with
parameters to your liking for example
the fee rate might be too low or too
high or
you want to coinjoin with like
a larger minimum input amount or
something like that
um we still need to kind of think this
through but um
uh it seems reasonable to just support
um like uh a specific user
um asking um i mean it's probably not
gonna be exposed in the front end
directly just because it's a kind of a
low level feature but
um there's no technical reason and i
think no game theoretical reason why
uh the coordinator should not support uh
the like the ability to just
uh ask for a new round to be created um
and and yeah so i'm optimistic about
these kinds of
possibilities opening up
okay cool um maybe i think one
topic just to rehash and to dive deeper
is
the benefits of the amount consolidation
of two users
uh maybe you will yeah if you have some
further thoughts on
this page on similar type of
amount consolidation
um so that was kind of implied by the
scenario
i was describing earlier
just to get everybody on the same page
um the idea
uh behind uh so i i i'm hesitant to call
that pay join just because page join
kind of implies
uh more it implies uh the steganographic
features as well so
uh i think like a pay-to-end point over
wabi-sabi
or a credential payment or something
like that is perhaps a better term but
the idea is
like let's say alice wants to pay bob
uh some amount she registers uh inputs
uh greater than that amount and uh
produces
uh in her registration she requests um
uh a credential worth the payment amount
and then she just gives that to bob
um alternatively she could ask bob for a
credential request and then
uh she has uh no opportunity to use it
herself but
in either case there's no theft concern
bob can then go and
and use this to um register uh his
output
uh for the the received amount
uh or he can consolidate it with his own
inputs to
get uh better privacy uh and this is
nice because
it protects um alice's inputs from
bob's uh prying eyes and uh
vice versa uh and um
um yeah it's uh like
that that's kind of how you would have
to do it anyway for like the simple case
um what i would be
kind of like more interested uh in
hearing uh
uh ben and nadav's thoughts um
like in the in the scenario where the
coordinator
um is kind of like mediating the the con
the bets themselves
um how like
especially in a uh like in that
settlement setting
um what kind of information would the
coordinator
need to uh to know and what what kind of
information
uh like do the individual users need to
exchange in order to to get that
settlement going because
i think that's um
kind of the logical continuation of uh
this this type of pay to endpoint uh
approach well real quick uh before
the dav and ben answer that in a naive
case
we're losing this isn't there still some
change output from each other
you're still obscuring things for a
third party observer
where that payment looks like a single
user's change output
uh so you were breaking up but
um if i uh i think
if i understand correctly then yes i
mean you're you're
not disclosing that there even was a
payment and
further you'd be breaking um the
the sort of heuristical assumption that
um
you can partition the transaction
uh into like one
set of inputs and outputs per user
that's going to balance to zero
um so that this is like
further helps to to break down the
common owner uh
in uh input heuristic um but
um like i i'm not sure what you meant
in the chat by uh uh passing an output
credential for unmixed change
uh the question i'm saying like if if i
put my input in there and get my mixed
outputs
and then give you an unmixed change
output
like that will look like i'm just
getting my unmixed change back but i
paid you
and even though like we still see that
graph between the two of us
like nobody else can interpret that
graph correctly
yes and that is a much simpler scenario
because there's no interactivity there's
no paint to end point all you need to do
is give me an address and i register
you know some output with your address
um like in the the pay to endpoint
scenario
um you do have much better counter pri
uh party privacy
um because they're like the only thing i
learned is
like what credential am i giving you i i
don't learn
how you're actually using it
and of course you you can in theory
combine it with uh
your unrelated input credentials which i
don't know about
and then the the payment amount is also
hidden and never appears in the
transaction
so many many privacy benefits
um to go back to nothing much as
original question i think um
i think like to have the coordinator
like be doing like
um like acting as like a watchtower um i
think all you'd have to give them
is like the oracle that they'll be
fetching from to get the signature
and then like your actual outcome
signatures so
doing so you kind of reveal what your
contract is to the
actual coordinator but uh
you also then get like this kind of
watchtower thing where you know they can
close it for you and you don't need to
like be online and make sure you do it
which is a huge ux improvement ben are
you talking about the
the two of two situation or there are a
bunch of two of two outputs
yeah yeah i guess if you have like you
know like gotcha or yeah i was just
going to mention in that case
uh really what you can use generally
speaking is a watchtower and you know if
coordinators are
some kind of watch tower in the future
they can also be used for that purpose
but you can also just use like
normal uh dlc enabled watch towers in
the future
uh but but yeah go ahead and talk about
the nfn case if you want
yeah so if you like if you had like a a
50 or 50
like kind of thing um i think you still
reveal your
your contract in that way maybe less so
no i think you would have to reveal
quite a bit
uh actually in this case which is why
you need kind of other obfuscation
methods if i'm not mistaken
all of the contract execution
transactions are now like
aggregate amongst all 50 peers and they
all have to
sign the the yeah the
uh closing transactions for everyone and
so they see
kind of what the output values are and
so you
you need to do some obfuscation on them
i think uh
ben is that right yeah i guess um you do
get the benefit that like where the
coordinator
won't know like which address is going
to like which
user so you do like they'll know like
you know this person
or this address gets paid out if this uh
you know
the price of bitcoins 10k or whatever
but they don't know directly like which
user registered the
payout address so you get the benefit of
you know hiding that but
they still can see like what the payout
curve is for each address
yes but you might actually be able to do
some amount decomposition of these
payout transactions that's right
right so you have one input with one
bitcoin and you break that down into 0.4
and 3.6
for example naively said but of course
what you uh do i i don't think that uh
it will require necessarily more signing
but uh i think what happens is that
rather than
everyone passing around their
contract info the the thing that's used
essentially their payout curve
for oracle as like what the oracle says
is the x-axis
and their payout is the y they take
their payout curve instead
and they break it up into pieces with
cancelling out noise
um and register multiple outputs and
then pass around these nonsensical
noise full payout curves
as if they're coming from different
people and so
everyone should have pretty nonsensical
uh if
if this works out anyway again i haven't
looked into it deep enough but
uh everyone should be able to pass
around somewhat nonsensical
payout curves uh where each person is
actually getting the aggregate of
multiple payout curves but no one else
knows
like what that looks like um
then hopefully that that mitigates
things a little bit
and furthermore once you have everyone's
payout curves you can construct
for yourself um deterministically
all of the uh closing transactions that
you need to sign
and validate signatures of okay
yeah that makes sense so like if you
have like say like 50 users you'd end up
with like
100 or like 200 actual payout outputs
but um you know there's still 50 users
so some some of them are getting
multiple
yeah but by the way we've done
especially well did a lot of research on
this amount decomposition
and currently like if we assume that
every new user knows the inputs
of the of the users of this current draw
on the point join
and it seems that's the same case here
right every user knows at least the
inputs
of uh of this amount uh and
then you can already make some privacy
optimized amount organization for the
outputs and the payout curves um
it's like it's but that benefits from
having standard amounts
right so if you would have multiple
standard demands
when users choose some of them and they
choose depending on what other inputs
were registered
yeah and i guess in theory you could
even have
uh i guess maybe it's it's easier if
everyone always has the same number of
outputs but you could
even play with that as like a parameter
to mess around with is you could have
more outputs on like some oracle
outcomes
as opposed to others if say you're
receiving more or something like this
i actually would guess i'm not sure but
i have an intuition that it's better for
privacy if it's not sure
how many exact outputs you have like if
it's if there's an
arbitrary like an ambiguous room between
one output or zero outputs
and i don't know 21 outputs whatever the
the maximum value is uh that seems to be
more
private because you then don't know how
many siblings each other
yeah so you could have i guess payout
curves that um
look noisy and are zero in lots of
places
and everyone just filters out dust
outputs every time or something like
this
or maybe there's a more sophisticated
way of doing that um
so that you don't actually see that
i think it's actually like orthogonal
like if you
look at the amounts themselves from the
purely the coinjoin perspective and
you're able to
[Music]
create enough ambiguity between the
input amounts and the output amounts
i i think it's immaterial what the
script semantics of those outputs are
uh and whether or not like the the funds
are uh broken down uh afterwards they're
divided between uh two counterparties to
some bet
um like that doesn't really matter
uh like all you learn is that this was
split between two people but
uh the bet itself should be uh
like the total amount should not be uh
really um uh
uh like linkable to the the inputs of
both users like in this scenario you can
imagine the two counterparties are
kind of acting like one user uh the
combined like if you partition the
transaction and
uh look at only the subset of inputs and
outputs for those two users who are
transacting
um if they
uh construct the the bet amount uh like
the bet output amounts
in in such a way that uh there's no way
to infer
that subset um based on
uh all of the like the rest of the
transaction
it's sufficiently ambiguous and at that
point
um like it's not clear uh which inputs
are going into the bet at all and
and therefore it should not be linkable
to the specific user
um did you talk a bit more about the
net settlement stuff that you were
alluding to before
uh sure yeah so say like um
[Music]
i am entering into
say two dlcs uh and i'm a little bit
over
collateralized uh because
say there's like some uh
canceling out so to speak in my position
like i'm a bit long here i'm a bit short
here or something like this
um then uh if in
in a situation where you have uh kind of
both of those dlcs going in
in one place i can essentially
have um my two counter parties
essentially take on that bet somewhat
synthetically against each other and
like recover some of my own collateral
do those counterparties uh need to
coordinate
or are they only coordinating through
you
[Music]
um i i guess it kind of depends on what
the coordinated
setup looks like uh for for the actual
uh mixing stuff sorry i i shouldn't have
used that word
um like suppose uh in the non-coin joint
scenario
you're you're doing this kind of thing
um
the do the the two counterparties
uh that you have like do they need to
communicate
uh between them and exchange uh like
adapter signatures between them
or uh can they uh rely on you to
to transfer the information between them
uh i see um so so yeah if you want to do
netting stuff you actually do need
kind of something like a coin join
looking thing because
uh essentially you need like all three
parties inputs and
outputs and such to be in a single
transaction
in order to get back your collateral so
to speak
um so some amount of
coordination does need to happen um
i assume that there are different ways
of doing
this maybe ben is more well-versed
i think it'd be up to like the person
that's actually benefiting from the
netting to
be able to figure out how to do it
correctly because um
you know their states are like over
collateralizing
that they can take it out they'd have to
um negotiate that with their peers to
like change the actual contract to be
like
uh to benefit them to get the lot to be
like less
collateralized at least that's my
understanding
i don't know i think uh didn't ichiro
write the
like initial paper on it he's probably
the best one to ask but
he's obviously not here
[Music]
yeah i think it's pretty much uh similar
to
what you have in mind though ben
yeah but i guess short answer is um
it's likely easiest if they are
coordinating with one another but
there's
likely other ways of
making things more obfuscated or
something
okay guys just in case we are making
questions and comments just
to keep the wheel rolling right but
anyone can make questions in fact it's
good if we
call this section q a now
right because i think most of the topics
are
are already covered and if in fact
the advanced topics are already
covered so feel free to
to write the hand
well i kind of missed the first uh
19 minutes or so but kind of just the
general topic of
blurring dlcs and nesting them into a
coin join
i mean it seems like there's a lot of
wins that you can have here
but it does kind of worry me that that
implicitly transitions the model of a
coin join for those users
to um you can get screwed or things can
go wrong if you lose
stateful data as opposed to it's
literally impossible for something to go
wrong here
um so i think an important thing to note
is there are kind of uh
two different ways of of doing this one
of which is
um essentially just having a coin join
where some of the outputs are like these
two of twos that are dlc funding outputs
themselves
um and you know those two of twos once
we have taproot become
just single pub keys anyway uh and
if you are doing things this way then um
i don't believe that parties who aren't
doing dlcs become affected
by parties that are doing dlcs inside of
the same mix
if that well i mean they shouldn't in
either case unless i'm missing something
but it's just kind of like that's
that that's an implicit risk i think
that should be
like that that is deserving of like a
big warning screen
that like things can go wrong if you
lose these transactions
you know what i mean well like you still
just have like
things can go wrong if you lose these
transactions you know what i mean
well like you still just have like
things can go wrong if you lose these
transactions
you know oh boy what's happening well
like um
things can go wrong if you lose these
transactions you know oh boy what's
happening
well like um this can go wrong
if you lose these transactions you know
oh boy what's happening
well like um everything this can go
wrong if you lose these transactions
you know oh boy what's happening well
like um
things
[Music]
yeah um i guess shinobi can
can you elaborate on how this is
different from just entering into a
normal dlc
in terms of state well i just mean it's
like
kind of putting these two options
together implicitly assumes that
one piece of software is going to be
capable of both and i just feel like you
know
burying a million options like that like
something should be
explicit about that you know what i mean
like there's no difference between
another
dlc
do you think
yes i did it but it
comes again so
that's where we have the passport yeah
um to get back to the adults in the
space who want to have adult
conversations about things there's so
many of them
um well they get back to it there's not
too much uh
like different intermingling maybe ben
is
because right at the end of the day you
you could have like your
mixing black box and your dlc black box
and
like one message needs to be passed from
one to the other
um i don't look specifically the one
that has
the funding tx id in it i don't think
that there's
much else yeah yeah like all you need is
for the dlc software it's like a funding
tx id for everything
and then that should be able to handle
everything else so it wouldn't be a huge
uh like complexity issue or anything
like that
so you guys are just talking like api
hooking
two pieces of software together not like
rolling all of this into like the wasabi
ui or anything
that's right uh although that sounds
like yeah then that that was a bad
question on my part then got you
no worries but for the nfn mix then
that's kind of its own custom thing but
that kind of assumes that everyone
involved is doing specific dlc stuff
okay yeah where you're registering two
of two outputs
hopefully you can uh and in the future
you know
just single pub key outputs then uh
essentially what you'll do is you'll
have like a callback
where um when you get the thing you need
to sign before you sign
the actual like funding or the the
mixing transaction
you like go make a call out to the dlc
api
do all that stuff and then come back and
do this last
okay all right that makes sense then i
guess
uh ignore shinobi's bike shedding troll
concerns
maybe a question on some different
regard that we did not talk about
how about optimizations uh that you used
for
these arbitrary amounts price
settlements can you maybe speak a bit
more
sure um yeah so
generally speaking uh you know if you're
thinking about dlcs as like a black box
you think about
like there's some set of outcomes
you create a transaction for each of
those outcomes that pays out
however it's supposed to for that
outcome and then you generate
adapter signatures um but
uh you know this works great for most
like
betting but if you're uh say
doing something where the outcome is a
number or you know there's just
a ton of outcomes and they're structured
um
then you have um
kind of this problem or a couple
different problems but
mainly the the problem is that uh you
have like
let's say a hundred thousand possible
outcomes
or or something like this when maybe
especially usu usually it's the case
that you only really
care about like some small subset of
those
and if it's anything above a certain
number or below a certain number
then you just have some like edge case
like
okay this person gets all the money or
something like this
um so what we do is we have the oracles
numeric oracles specifically sign
uh each binary digit each bit
of the outcome individually and then we
can essentially construct
uh outcomes uh
using digit prefixes instead of the
entire
list of digits so instead of requiring
that there's a separate outcome so to
speak
or it's a different outcome for every
different number you can have for
example if you ignore the last digit
and you just look at all of the digit
prefix up to the last digit
then you can have um
an outcome that corresponds to two
possible
numbers and then if you ignore two
digits that's four possible numbers and
so on
and so you can essentially for example
say if everything above
uh 100k um
is is just like the same outcome
basically then what you can do is you
can decompose that very very large
interval
into only logarithmically many um
cets essentially or contract execution
transactions
um and so and then furthermore
uh we we introduced some amount of
rounding so this is like negotiated both
parties are okay
with the amount of rounding that happens
um and you uh
essentially say round to the nearest
hundred satoshi's or the nearest
thousand satoshis or something like this
um and then by doing that
you uh can get more kind of flat pieces
which can be compressed by the same
mechanism into logarithmically many
you know adapter signatures that you
need
and so in practice what this means is
that even
relatively complicated uh you know
financial contracts
uh on numeric outcomes on prices uh end
up
with only say a couple thousand uh
adapter signatures or cases that you
you've decomposed it into rather than
having to cover like all
you know hundred two hundred thousand um
and then furthermore for for
multi-oracle stuff there's also some
fanciness that we do um
where essentially you you do something
similar where
uh agreement between two
um agreement between two oracles
is essentially constitutes like you take
one of these digit prefixes from one
oracle
and then you construct the digit prefix
for like the second
oracle that covers um
that uh same uh or what the first oracle
said
with like say some allowed amount of
error so we even cover cases where
you have multiple oracles and they don't
sign exactly the same thing
they can be like some amount off
um say if you're for example
using like kraken and bitfinex
and um gemini
or something like that as three price
oracles then uh you can have it so that
so long as
any two of them are within 128
of the btc usd of the same btc usd price
or something like this then um your
contract will execute
so yeah all sorts of fanciness
and and stuff happening there and
there's some more optimizations that
i'm working on that maybe use some like
verifiable encryption and stuff like
that to try and get
the uh the scaling for adding
new oracles down to something more
reasonable
yeah i'd be happy to talk more about it
of course but at this point
i'm probably just rambling unless
someone has questions
i'm just curious do you think that this
is anyhow interesting research useful
for conjoint
can you say that one more time like do
you think that there's some nice
similar ideas that we can use to
optimize for coin joints
in the non-dlc case i mean or is it just
completely different research
i would think if if there is any overlap
it would be
in kind of the coordination of the
uh outputs and such
um because you know we have like some
pretty succinct coordination between the
two parties
on um you know essentially like the
contingent like you know
if the oracle says any of these things
then here are my outputs in all of those
cases so we have like these nice
compressed
uh essentially like seeds from which you
are you know contracts from which you
derive
all of the transaction information but
um i guess for a regular coin joint you
just have one transaction so maybe
that's not a big problem
yeah i think where the most overlap is
is honestly like
on the off chain side where you're
finding counterparties like um
like we've like looked into like
different ways we could you know have a
place to find like a counterparty for
the bets you want to make and like you
could do like you know you just have
like a central place
like someone's like a wasabi coordinator
or you could have something where it's
like
join market where it's like you know a
kind of decentralized kind of thing
where you're finding
there's no like coordinator to find you
counterparties so
it's um it's a different way to do it
and we're you know we haven't really
there's probably going to be like
multiple different ways to do it similar
to how the coin joint landscape
is today so i think that'll be probably
the place where there's the most overlap
yeah i think the amount organization
might be interesting for you guys
like based on the inputs of other users
how can we optimize the outputs of us
uh so to gain more privacy i think this
is
uh like non-coinjoin cryptography
related things
uh that might be interesting for you
yeah and i guess also uh you know if we
are doing
some kind of dlc mixing stuff in the
future then also the
amount decomposition uh things
might be some overlap there
uh the one maybe relating question how
do you
get consensus on the fee priority for
this transaction
um so currently this is done
via um essentially
you know you can choose whether or not
to accept a certain fee rate but
afterwards uh everything is
uh fee bumpable using a child pace for
parent where the child
is replaced by fee enabled
so it's um yeah
i guess you there there's always the
uh you know lots of complex ways to
handle these kinds of things i think
right now
the dual funded lightning channel
proposal just has like the initiator pay
all the fees because it's simpler
um but we decided to
kind of split the fees between the two
parties and then
for for the fee rate that's in like say
the offer message
and then um everything beyond that is
done just by
fee bumping um
yeah yeah two notes here i mean for
somewhat obvious reasons
rbf is not possible in large coin joins
or not reasonable to do
because you have to resign everyone has
to resign that's right and for
dlcs it's not possible either it's only
the child
of inner child pays for parents so like
if you spend your change
then the thing you're using to spend
your change is what you would rbf with
yeah yeah that's smart actually but the
issue here still
is with uh like the the size of the coin
joint
like you have to rb you have to try to
pay for parent the entire fee for the
coin joint
um well max you could do that out of the
change input or output that wasabi is
getting fees in
once you you implement like fee
credentials
that could potentially be a thing where
users
pay for that air quotes with the fee
credentials but it's just that single
output wasabi got the mix fees with that
could actually do
the rbf child pace repairing hybrid
if like a coin joined stalling in the
mempool
yes maybe
yeah actually maybe and like users can
pay at any time and maybe every hour
wasabi will do an rbf of the child
uh to v-bump and if there were
was no fee bumping fee credential being
sent in that hour then it also doesn't
do the rbf yeah actually
and that would be totally open for any
user it's not like everybody has to chip
in
or split it up it's just like if i'm
super impatient
take my fee credentials make that happen
faster
plus the user doesn't have to spend his
own chaincoin right which would reveals
his high time preference fingerprint
while instead if the coordinator spends
his v output
with the rbf thing then we only know
that some user in this coin joint had
the
high time preference and paid for the p
bunk but we don't know which one it was
i don't think that would work uh because
you would need to provide
uh like all of the rbf scenarios
of which there will be exponentially
many um
in the size of the transaction for every
single user's
um like every ordering of users choosing
to bump
fees uh should subtract some different
amount
and then all of those outcomes have to
be pre-signed uh
except for why though we're no we're
we're not talking about the coin join
transaction itself
we're talking about a child transaction
with with the output
forget what i said so it's like that
naturally yeah that would be
super private um that would allow any
user to accelerate the coin join without
any privacy damage on their part
and then three um like that could go to
the extreme that wasabi
literally burns that entire fee income
for that round in two fees
but they're not going to do it unless
they redeem tokens and then have the
right to spend
some reserved utxos on themselves so
that like
that's a complete privacy win and should
totally balance out on wasabi's hunt
yep because we already got the vidcon
earlier
and by the way maybe even users who are
not part of this coin join
can issue a feedback right because as
long as you have long-lived feed
credentials
any user can pay it
[Music]
nadav you are a whiz kid that inspires
genius ideas everywhere you go
to be fair uh i credit antoine riyard
with
all of the fee bumping stuff i just uh
read his spec and gave a review
you still inspired something here
because you are wizkid
yeah but uh again the the statement
still holds right
one user has to pay to feed bump the
transaction of every user
and so uh your set per
by it is going to be very small um
but your nominal amount of sets still
going to be quite large
if you want to make a meaningful
difference yeah though
you know you could also kind of view it
as some kind of like crowd funding for
fees
scenario where you know it'll go
or maybe that's not a good analogy
because you also are
you want these or there's important
things in these and different people
will have
different um preferences but you know in
theory you could have multiple people
doing fee bumping and the the fee
bumping would all then kind of get
aggregated but
yeah some people can always be kind of
free riders in that scenario
if they don't have too much stake too
much at stake
yeah but the nice thing is is that the
free riders are contained within one
transaction
because the alternative approach to
efficient pe estimation
is what we used before in wasabi 1.0 but
that is not turned off
is to make child pays for parent of
unconfirmed coinjoin rounds
so to allow unconfirmed coins all the
coinjoin outputs to remix
and the the coordinator slightly
increased each
round's fee a little bit which was
efficient to get all coin joints
confirmed reasonably quickly reasonably
cheap um
but the downside was that if you were
the first participant in the first round
of
uh coin join like the parents
transacting first unconfirmed
then you paid very little piece while
you were like at the end
of the chain number 15 or something
right your
your fee rate got higher and you don't
even get faster confirmation for that
because you carry like 14 parents uh
that you still have to confirm
um gotcha
so with this approach at least this
revival problem stays within one
transaction
i guess that's as small as it can get
i mean that's perfect though because
like that
just removes all of the dependency
limits in the mempool except for
remixing
right because each thing would be its
own parallel
um child pays for a parent that's what
you're saying right
yeah exactly each coin is i'm sorry each
conjoint transaction is one unconfirmed
transaction and because the coordinator
requires that
all inputs to the coinjoin have been
confirmed already
um this means that no coin from the
unconfirmed coin joint transaction can
be registered in
a new coin joint transaction and
therefore we don't have child base
repairing chains
go ahead adam sorry i
i i would have a question but it's a bit
different
topic is that okay sure go ahead
so i i was i was thinking about
the industrial things
some of you might have seen on twitter
and and i believe i
i get to the end of how far i can
think about that when i properly went
through the issue but
it would be really nice if uh if to hear
what you guys think about that
so the start is that
there is a perverse incentive
for the coinjoin
coin joint fees with the current wasabi
which is which is that
the more user the coinjoin have
the i think exponentially more
fee is being paid out by the queen join
rounds if i'm correct and
there is a perverse incentive for the
coordinator
to to add their own users
so what do you guys think about this and
i
i will i will not say what i think just
see if we get this similar conclusions
or not
do you mean in the context of dlcs or
coinjoins in general
no we currently coinjoin
fee coordinator fee structure
i agree 100 i think it's a problem
and uh especially
when in combination with the like the
discount there's additional perverse
incentives
for um like individual users to
to register specific outputs and uh
that can be combined to to make sibling
by somebody other than
than the coordinator uh also are a
little bit cheaper
so it's not just the coordinator
i think it's perfectly possible to
address it
like this is why i've been proposing a
flat
uh like flat rate some percentage of
mining fee perhaps or
um and on top of that uh
doing some sort of uh like discount
model for um
encouraging like a pro privacy behavior
so for example like bringing in um
an older input something which destroys
a large number of coin days
um this is kind of like fidelity bonds
in join market
like you know that that input has not
been sibling any of the
rounds that were concurrent with this
output not being spent like after it was
confirmed
uh this could not have been used this
liquidity could not have been used to
civil
other rounds um so uh it's good to
incentivize
uh that kind of behavior as well um
or all right so is it a perverse
being centi yes okay let's let's keep it
simple and only talk about the
coordinator for now does anyone not
agree with
this or or or or we can move on and
and everyone agrees no part with the
coordinator
i mean that's a special unique case
because
anything that they could do is free and
that's like the whole
problem with the fee schedule and
sibling it's you have to balance between
on one end
it being so cheap that you can sybil
all day long and on the other end it
being
so expensive that people aren't going to
remix
which is one of the most important
properties of a system like this
so it's like if you're talking the fee
schedule i mean
i i wouldn't talk about like perverse
incentives i would be talking about
where is that middle spot
where you accomplish both of those
things it's not
too expensive for people to be remixing
but it's not so
cheap that you can just flood the system
with liquidity and sibling
we'll get to that because i mean
yeah sorry max go ahead uh if i made
just quickly
uh an important distinction here is uh
mining fees and coordinator fees
are very separate um so chernobyl your
point
stands when coordinator fees dominate
over mining fees but not vice versa
touche
yeah and uh one other quick thing is
that this
cheaper remixing for high quality coins
especially when it when we add a timeout
benefit
right so utxod is destroyed if that
count is high
then you get a cheaper coordination or
mining fee this has similar
denial of service protections as
fidelity bonds
though i would say weaker because
fidelity's bonds you actually cannot
spend the coin in this lock-up period
while um well with this type you could
have spent the coin
but because you did not spend it you get
cheaper fees
so it still improves denials or
increases the number of service costs
just in opportunity cost of not spending
these coins
yeah i mean i think that's a perfect way
to balance that
all right so so this is the perverse
incentive that there is no
no question about this now is it a
civilian incentive and i
actually did not i was not
not able to to come to the end of this
this question
i i my conclusion was maybe
but you know what the sibila keys is
when
most of the participants are actually
one entity right so
the question is would this lead
to to such situation where most of the
participants are
are are one entity is is this
is this this instant devices
that much so that would happen
you know what i mean well i mean aside
from the coordinator i don't see
how that could be the case if you're
paying fees every time and i mean if
if the coordinator wants to sybil their
mixing pool
i mean all they have to pay is mining
fees
everything else is free but with anybody
else
i mean if you're paying fees for every
mix round i don't see how that
encourages it that's a disincentive
like that's one problem i have with
samurai
is their fee schedule incentivizes
lots and lots of remixing but the fact
that you only pay
once and everything else is free i could
just buy
a new utxo on cash app every day and
feed that into whirlpool
and just let that sybil all day for free
could something you do to like prevent
the
um coordinator from having like the
ability to um
civil by just only paying mining fees
just have like
say like half or like a third of the
actual
coordinator fee just like be like sent
like an op return like burn or
like have it like donated to like hrf or
you know
some fund well that's kind of what i
think like nothing much was getting at
with modeling
the mixing fees off of the mining fees
so that's uh that's always balanced the
correct way there
um you can correct me if i'm wrong
nothing much
um yeah like you could make the flat
the sorry the coordinator fees either be
completely flat
so like some percentage of the
amount regardless of how many other
inputs and outputs are in the
transaction regardless of how much
liquidity is in the transaction
um that could be like a a linear
function of the amount or the
weight and if you make it just a linear
function of the weight well then
you know that it's proportional to the
mining fees
um it doesn't really matter like which
of these specific
scenarios and it could be like a
constant function not necessarily a
linear function
oh all right all right so i didn't fully
fleshed out but
i think somehow the
because if you think about it if there
are
99 real users then
it makes sense for the coordinator to
join in to be the 100th one because 99
people will pay
after another appear 0.003 percent
right so so it makes sense if you're
thinking about the big numbers
because then you will get 99.003 percent
but if you are thinking about the small
numbers
one if there is only one user does it
work for the coordinator to get into the
round
and the answer is it doesn't because
that's only one times zero zero zero
three percent and the coordinator will
pay more mining fees than
how much it would gain fees from
that person so i think the question
here where is the equilibrium where
the bitcoin fees
you know so yeah the intercept is where
uh i think it's roughly like 20 000
satoshi's
uh on average uh in coordinator fees
um for like a um i may be
misremembering but like 0.1
times the number of users um
times 0.003 i think uh
percent sorry so another two zeros but
like you can calculate
the uh expected value for the
coordinator from
like or not even expected just the value
for the coordinator for um
uh that additional user and if the
marginal cost in terms of the current
mining fees of adding
a single input uh and registering
another
fake 0.1 output um is
less than that then there's a clear
incentive for the the coordinator to do
that
so it's it's just a function of um the
current fee rate for the the transaction
and
um because i mean you could do this
repeatedly
uh so long as the cost of an additional
input and output is less than
uh the the figure the um
without multiplying by the number of
users because the total amount paid by
the user
that usually sums to um several tens of
thousands of satoshis
as long as that increment is uh greater
than
the marginal cost of an additional fake
user well uh
that's a linear function so it's the
same regardless of how many
inputs and outputs were already added
okay so what's interesting here is that
you know it might seem like like
there is a civil issue
but it doesn't because it definitely
doesn't make sense for one people two
people
three people five people 10 people maybe
at 10 people it starts to make sense for
the coordinator but
you know there is there is a line
somewhere where it starts to make sense
and so it doesn't mean that the
coordinator
is instant device to take
99 of the the existing users or
something
like that it it just means even
the coordinator participates with more
users it
it pays more mining fees you know what i
mean like
like there must be a line there where it
starts to make sense but maybe it's at
50 people
i i don't know right it's a function of
the fee rate
so at one satoshi per byte and let's say
100 bytes
per per fake user uh let's say it costs
100 satoshi's to pay them
mining fees for another civil user
if you can extract more than 100
satoshis and coordinator fees from the
target user or users
uh right so like the more users you're
targeting the less powerful
your civil attack is for the
anonymization but the more
uh the more fees you can extract
out of those uh victims um so there's
just a tipping point there
right it's uh it's just the intercept of
two lines
um exactly exactly right
but i'm actually gonna create a graph
very nicely in this
this episode but uh but
this means it's not a civil incentive
at least not in the sense that people
are using
it to be right because there is no
incentive to do it for smaller number of
users so
i would say not the number of users that
you're saying it sure
it's well anyway you know what i mean
it's not a civil incentive not nothing
the civil incentive that
while the coordinator is insane
incentivized to be anonymize everyone
no it's very far from the case actually
it's a free ride incentive
well no it's worse than a freeride
incentive because the coordinator
actually increases its revenue
if it does this but um uh
even if like the the the tipping point
like whether or not it makes sense for a
civil attack or only for extracting
additional fees
uh that entirely depends on the like
whether or not the
uh mining fee rate is low enough uh and
if
the minimum rate is like one satoshi per
byte um
that's actually not that high i think
it's usually much higher than that i
think it's like on on average more like
10 or 20 uh at the
the lowest rate so that implies that yes
adam you're you're correct it's not
really a direct incentive because uh
an additional like fake user uh
would not the the cost would not be
covered by the additional fees of just
a single user
all right so now it's it's worth asking
the question
that you know here is a weak civil
incentive or
or strange civil incentive
but you know there are these incentives
for
cbl what do you guys think can you
identify
some
so obviously it is reputation the most
the largest civil instantly and you know
it is also noticeable when you start to
do that
um do you guys say bye
so for example we can't tell with the
current wasabi that there is no cbl
happening or at least not this kind of
civilian
why is because we have 10 000
bitcoin monthly volume and
the direct way the non-noticeable way to
see bill it would be
if we would be most of the participants
of that of the 10 000 bitcoin if we
would be
bringing in that fresh those are fresh
bitcoins not the
actual coinjoin volume that's 40 000 but
the fresh bitcoins monthly is ten
thousand so
in order to cbl unnoticeably
we would have to have like nine thousand
bitcoin or something
crazy like that but you know if we would
have nine thousand
five thousand bitcoin then the last
thing that we would care about
is the perverse fiends and the beach
at at best it's
it's a couple of bitcoins not
five thousand you know what i mean it it
wouldn't make sense in that case
do you guys agree or disagree with that
mostly agree i i think it's you know you
need to
actually crunch the numbers and figure
out like at fee rate x
this is how much liquidity you would
need to create
a fake uh graph of this size in order to
make you know the hide the liquidity
and you can reduce it to like what is
the liquidity requirement and what is
the marginal cost or
profit for the coordinator to do like
an additional round um and
and uh parametrize that by how many real
users are in the round
we could also execute okay let's say we
agree
then i i say that i i wasn't completely
correct there because
we could also execute a severe
attack from less money you know from
remixing
actually i think that's what you were
referring to by by liquidity right
i guess the confirmation something like
that
uh yeah um it's not just that it's
also uh like how much in mining fees are
you paying to
create like a fake graph that
does not look like remixing which is uh
like that that's a distinction between
fresh and remixed coins right
okay so but we also know that
you know because this what what the cbr
would lead to
in this case if we don't have don't have
if we are not matching the users
users money with our own money with
multiplies of our of the users money
we would have to have that much then if
if that's happening
then we would see a very high number of
remixes and it's only 20 to 30 percent
so that's not that that
actually proves that there is no
this kind of cbl which may or may not be
severe happening
does that does that make sense is there
anything wrong with that
uh no i think that's correct but i mean
you need to take into account the
possibility that
you mix coins and then you create some
sort of
fake spending graph and eventually you
cycle that back
into the mix with you know a bunch of
fake transactions in between which also
costs you mining fees
probably a lot more than the the mining
fees for the coin join
in order to simulate fresh bitcoins that
are actually just getting recycled by
the coordinator
that incurs the significant cost and i
think it's it's uh
you know the if you look at the topology
uh
of the actual graph on the blockchain uh
it should be fairly straightforward to
estimate that cost or even
just measure it yeah but for what it's
worth the dumplings repo only uses
one like you can fool the dumpling
repository into thinking it's fresh
bitcoin but just making one transaction
so fresh bitcoins are only the actual
outputs of the coin joints
being inputs of the next coin join but
if there's even one hop of the single
user transaction in there
it's not considered fresh anymore all
right or sorry it is considered
yes and i mean that uh if you
are thinking adversarially then the
coordinator
uh like probably anticipated that and
created uh you know anticipated the
scenario where
the dumbling's repository was updated to
take that into account etc etc
you can still reduce that to a cost
in in mining fees at the bottom line
so anyway just to to
to sum up so is it a perverse incentive
yes is it a civil incentive
um not really not in the stands
where people are using it because
maybe it would be a big civil incentive
something like that but
not even in the technical sense because
in the technical sense the majority of
the
the user should be controlling
the the volume and you know is there a
cbl
no there is no cbl because
it's noticeable which is a disincentive
and the final question is that why did
we not
change that it's because you know
the fee structure is is actually pretty
fair
because you gain
more privacy you pay more but
that's not the real reason the real
reason is because the fee structure
is not something that you know that's
the first agreement you have with all
your users and your if you are
unilaterally
um just changing it without a very good
reason like
like wasabi 2.0 which needs
change anyway because of the protocol
then then you know like like you're not
changing around with the
most fundamental parameters
that's good music by the way
what music uh i can see someone is
sharing their screen again
yeah but guys can you kick him out
trying but doesn't work
yeah we need to use a private jet see
then maybe just let the
let the music go for a while and
and then the live stream that would be a
nice ending
yeah yeah maybe we should end the stream
now
wasabi research club cat hacked
tomorrow headlines
wasabi attacked
can't have fun can't be an adult
because stupid children
all right thank you
uh any closing thoughts that uh
ben or nadav want to bring up
we should set up uh dlc contracts for
whether or not there's a civil attack on
what saw me
here we go oh yeah
i was gonna say thanks for having us
this was fun always down to talk to you
guys um
yeah but thanks
thanks for coming
well thank you guys it was really
really you know just thinking back when
we started the wasabi research club
as uh as
exactly not exactly more than one year
ago then we were just
gonna have have some fun reviewing all
the privacy papers and
and you know uh putting them on youtube
and
and they're hoping that the authors of
the privacy paper appear because this is
publicity for them and then we can
pick their brains and ask our questions
and
and you know that that was fun and then
for a long time it was
it was just uh just just
just us basically thinking about all
kinds of privacy things and
it it it looks like you guys are taking
this to a completely new level
so i mean it's it's really
really awesome to to see so congrats for
these
yeah thank you i mean you guys are doing
awesome here the lobby i remember
like being when i was in college just
like watching all your
like the snicker one and the oh dear
and the uh you know all the different
like
uh mix it like mixed net ones that are
really interesting and yeah it's crazy
what you guys
are building now it's completely awesome
and i really like how it's all coming
together like i can totally see why we
saw the coin joints
that open and close dlc contracts or
lightning channels that then open and
close dlc contract
uh that's gonna be a wild wild world
yeah
guys we have uh again someone sharing
their screen
uh but yeah let's end the stream and
yeah i think this was a good episode
you know i'm listening to this music
like three times a day
super simple songs my my son really
loves it
i can't even hear the song but yeah